Finding Aid for Eva Jessye Collection
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Collected Programs
  - Theatrical Programs
    - Cabin in the Sky (Box 5)
    - Caviar to the General (Box 5)
    - Chalked Out (Box 5)
    - Charleston 1822 (Box 5)
    - The Cold Wind and the Warm (Box 5)
    - Come for a Song! (Box 5)
    - Critics' Choice (Box 5)
    - Cry the Beloved Country (Box 5)
    - Dance with your Gods (Box 5)
    - Dark Eyes (Box 5)
    - Death of Bessie Smith (Box 5)
    - Death of the Well-Loved Boy (Box 5)
    - Doin' It! (Box 5)
    - Don't Play Us Heap (Box 5)
    - Duel of Angels (Box 5)
    - Dybbuk (Box 5)
    - Farmers Hotel (Box 5)
    - Faust (Box 5)
    - Fiorello! (Box 5)
    - Flower Drum Song (Box 5)
    - Flying Colors (Box 5)
    - Free and Equal (Box 5)
    - The Great White Hope (Box 5)
    - Green Willow (Box 5)
    - Gypsy (Box 5)
    - Hallelujah, Baby (Box 5)
    - Head of the Family (Box 5)
    - Hello Dolly (Box 5)
    - A Hole in the Head (Box 5)
    - The Hooch (Box 5)
    - House of Flowers (Box 5)
    - How I Wonder (Box 5)
    - I'll Take My Stand (Box 5)
    - In Abraham's Bosom (Box 5)
    - Interlock (Box 5)
    - Janie (Box 5)
    - Kiss Me Kate (Box 5)
    - Lady Day (Box 5)
    - Lonesome Train (Box 5)
    - Look to the Lilies (Box 5)
    - Little Foxes (Box 5)
    - Locust (Box 5)
    - Loss of Roses (Box 5)
    - Lost in the Stars (Box 5)
    - Maggie Flynn (Box 5)
    - Martha (Box 5)
    - Members of the Wedding (Box 5)
    - More Stately Mansions (Box 5)
    - Mrs. Patterson (Box 5)
    - Much Ado About Nothing (Box 5)
    - Mutatto (Box 5)
    - Native Son (Box 5)
    - No Place to be Somebody (Box 5)
    - No Way Out (Box 5)
    - Of Mice and Men (Box 5)
    - Olney Theatre (Box 5)
    - On Cobweb Twine (Box 5)
    - Only in America (Box 5)
    - Orpheus Descending (Box 5)
    - Ouanga (Box 5)
    - Period of Adjustment (Box 5)
    - Plaster Bambino (Box 5)
    - Ponder Heart (Box 5)
    - The Price (Box 5)
    - Purlle (Box 5)
    - The Respectful Prostitute (Box 5)
    - Rhinoceros (Box 5)
    - Shakespeare in Harlem (Box 5)
    - Showboat (Box 5)
    - Small Hours (Box 5)
    - Smiles of the World (Box 5)
    - Sound of Music (Box 5)
    - Stevedore (Box 5)
    - Sweet Bird of Youth (Box 5)
    - Sweet River (Box 5)
    - Swing It (Box 5)
    - Take Me Along (Box 5)
    - Tambourines to Glory (Box 5)
    - Tenderloin (Box 5)
    - They Shall Not Die (Box 5)
    - Thread of Scarlet (Box 5)
    - Three Men on a Horse (Box 5)
    - Too Many Boats (Box 5)
    - Torch Bearers (Box 5)
    - Toys in the Attic (Box 5)
    - Tropical Carnival (Box 5)
    - Un Ballo in Maschera (Box 5)
    - Walk Together Children (Box 5)
    - Warm Peninsula (Box 5)
    - Weekend (Box 5)
    - White Cargo (Box 5)
    - Who's Who, Baby? (Box 5)
    - World of My America (Box 5)
    - You Can't Take It With You (Box 5)
    - Oversized Posters (located in Box 14) (Box 5)
  - Concert Programs
    - Aldrich Adkins, Provenience of the Black Man (Box 5)
    - African-American Women Composers (Box 5)
    - Afro/American Total Theatre, Makin' It (Box 5)
    - Association for the Study of Negro Life and History, Annual Luncheon 1970 (Box 5)
    - Kenneth Brown Billups, Alpha to Omega 1962 (Box 5)
    - Bronze 5th Annual Jubilee 1982 (Box 5)
    - Charles Samuel Brown 1974 (Box 5)
    - Wayne S. Brown (Box 5)
    - Buffalo Arts and Music Youth Choral 1985 (Box 5)
    - Catskill Choral Society 1983 (Box 5)
    - Charles Sumner High School, Christmas Concert 1969-1970 (Box 5)
    - Christ Presbyterian Church, Nashville TN (Box 5)
    - Clarion University Black Arts Festival 1987 (Box 5)
    - Composers Concepts, Detroit 1978 (Box 5)
    - Celia Watts Cox Luncheon 1986 (Box 5)
    - Dance Genesis, Black Alliance Theatre 1975 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Music Settlement School 1964 (Box 5)
    - Detroit Music Ed Club, Annual Spring Luncheon (Box 5)
    - Detroit Public Schools Choral Festival 1970 (Box 5)
    - R. Nathaniel Dett, Triad Choral 1982 (Box 5)
    - Ella and Ellington, Your Heritage Concert 1976 (Box 5)
    - Duke Ellington, Sacred Concert 1968 (Box 5)
    - First Unitarian Church 1972 (Box 5)
    - Gardner C. Taylor Glee Club 1955 (Box 5)
    - Grosse Point Community Chorus 1962 (Box 5)
    - Grosse Pointe Summer Chorus 1964 (Box 5)
    - Henry Hadley Birthday Concert 1964 (Box 5)
    - Harlem Homecoming (Box 5)
    - Harlem Is Heaven 1986 (Box 5)
    - Harlem Philharmonic (Box 5)
    - James Tatum Trio Plus 1979 (Box 5)
    - Juneteenth 1994 (Box 5)
    - Joplin, MO 1981 (Box 5)
    - Langston University Concert Choir 1971 (Box 5)
    - Gloria Davis McCully Recital (Box 5)
    - Methodism for 2 Centuries 1984 (Box 5)
    - Michigan Men's Glee Club 1972 (Box 5)
    - Morgan State University Choir 1986 (Box 5)
    - Mother A.M.E Zion Church, Christmas (Box 5)
    - Musi-Carnival, Opus'69 (Box 5)
    - Opera Ebony 1986 (Box 5)
    - Our Lady St. Rose, KS 1979 (Box 5)
    - Willis Patterson (Box 5)
    - Philharmonic-Symphony Society of NY 1945 (Box 5)
    - Renaissance Concert Series 1986 (Box 5)
    - Earl Robinson, Town Hall, NYC 1963 (Box 5)
    - St. Martin Episcopal Church, NY 1971 (Box 5)
    - Music of Howard Swanson 1974 (Box 5)
    - Take Care (Box 5)
    - Tuskegee Choir (Box 5)
    - University of Michigan, Music of Black Americans 1971 (Box 5)
    - Voices Inc. Beauty of Blackness 1970 (Box 5)
    - Wayne State, Afro-American Music 1972 (Box 5)
    - Wayne State, Choral Union 1975 (Box 5)
    - Ora Williams, Songs (Box 5)
    - Oversized Posters (located in Box 14) (Box 5)
  - Lectures/Memorials
    - W.E.B. Dubois, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Program in Black American Culture, Smithsonian 1980 (Box 5)
    - Rhythm of America, Sissle and Eubie Blake 1967 (Box 5)
    - Republic of Upper Volta (Box 5)
    - Bill "Bojangles" Robinson 1949 (Box 5)
    - Tribute to Fatherhood (Box 5)
    - Washington Cathedral Summerfest (Box 5)
    - Women of Courage, Cuyahoga Community College (Box 5)
    - Oversized Posters (located in Box 14) (Box 5)
- Eva Jessye Clippings
  The Eva Jessye Clippings (.75 linear feet) series contains newspaper and magazine clipping and reviews about Jessye and her professional activities. These files remain unorganized, and consist of many duplicate items, fragile materials, and un-cited newspaper fragments.
  - Various newspaper and magazine clippings (Box 6)
- Black History Clippings
  The Black History Clippings Series (2.0 linear feet) consists of collected newspaper and magazine clippings concerning black history and biographical and promotional information on black artists and historical figures. This collection contains no primary source material. As secondary material, it has meager informational content. The folders are grouped into four subseries: Concert Singers and Instrumentalists, Composers and Arrangers, Chorus and Ensembles, and Writers, Poets, Dancers, Actors. Each subseries is ordered alphabetically. Clipping subjects include opera stars Jessye Norman and Leontyne Price, actor Paul Robeson, pianist Andre Watts, composer Wm. Grant Still, the ensemble Fisk Jubilee Singers, gospel singer Mahalia Jackson, blues and pop music artist such as Bessie Smith, Chuck Berry, W C Handy, The Mills Brothers., The Supremes, Billie Holiday plus many other actors/actresses, bandleaders, night club entertainers, dance ensembles, and cultural leaders.
  - Concert Singers and Instrumentalists (Box 7)
    - Allen, Betty (Box 7)
    - Anderson, Marian (Box 7)
    - Ashley, Bryan (Box 7)
    - Armstrong, Louis (Box 7)
    - Arroyo, Martina (Box 7)
    - Baits, Leon (Box 7)
    - Baker, Josephine (Box 7)
    - Belle, Gwendolya (Box 7)
    - Bibb, Leon (Box 7)
    - Billups, Kenneth (Box 7)
    - Black, Donald (Box 7)
    - Boatwright, McHenry (Box 7)
    - Bonds, Margaret (Box 7)
    - Brown, James (Box 7)
    - Brown, Thelma Waide (Box 7)
    - Brown, William (Box 7)
    - Cole, Francis (Box 7)
    - Combo, Marian (Box 7)
    - Cox, Bettie (Box 7)
    - Cunningham, Arthur (Box 7)
    - Davis, Miles (Box 7)
    - Davy, Gloria (Box 7)
    - Depaur, Leonard (Box 7)
    - Dillard, James (Box 7)
    - Dixon, Lucille (Box 7)
    - Dixon, Willie (Box 7)
    - Dobbs, Matiwilda (Box 7)
    - Driver, Alberta (Box 7)
    - Evanti, Lillian (Box 7)
    - Foster, Aleesa (Box 7)
    - Foster, William (Box 7)
    - Fraizel, James (Box 7)
    - Franklin, Aretha (Box 7)
    - Freeman, Paul (Box 7)
    - Frierson, Andrew (Box 7)
    - Grist, Reri (Box 7)
    - Hall, James (Box 7)
    - Hampton, Lionel (Box 7)
    - Hancock, Eugene (Box 7)
    - Harris, Hilda (Box 7)
    - Hampton, Lionel (Box 7)
    - Hayes, Roland (Box 7)
    - Haywood, Billie (Box 7)
    - Hinderas, Natalie (Box 7)
    - Holmes, Eugene (Box 7)
    - Hopkins, Sam (Lightning') (Box 7)
    - Horne, Lina (Box 7)
    - Hunter, Alberta (Box 7)
    - Jackson, Mahalia (Box 7)
    - Johnson, Hall (Box 7)
    - Jones, Betty (Box 7)
    - King, Coretta (Box 7)
    - King, Juanita (Box 7)
    - Lutcher, Nellile (Box 7)
    - Martin, Roberta (Box 7)
    - Mitchell, Leona (Box 7)
    - Miller, Olivette (Box 7)
    - Moore, Kermit (Box 7)
    - Moore, Melba (Box 7)
    - Nolan, Robert (Box 7)
    - Norman, Jessye (Box 7)
    - Patton, Anne (Box 7)
    - Perry, Richard (Box 7)
    - Phillips, Arthur (Box 7)
    - Porter, Karl Hampton (Box 7)
    - Price, Leontyne (Box 7)
    - Rhea, Julia (Box 7)
    - Sheppard, Lemuel (Box 7)
    - Shakensnider, Wilma (Box 7)
    - Shirley, George (Box 7)
    - Simpson, Eugene (Box 7)
    - Smith, Bessie (Box 7)
    - Smith, William C. (Box 7)
    - Speights, Dorothy (Box 7)
    - Spivey, Victoria (Box 7)
    - Stevenson, Delcina (Box 7)
    - Townsend, Larry (Box 7)
    - Tyler, Veronica (Box 7)
    - Verrett, Shirley (Box 7)
    - Walker, Frances (Box 7)
    - Ward, Clara (Box 7)
    - Waters, Jeanette (Box 7)
    - Watts, Andre (Box 7)
    - Weathers, Felicia (Box 7)
    - Williams, Clyde (Box 7)
    - Williams, Peral (Box 7)
    - Wolf, Howlin' (Box 7)
  - Composers and Arrangers
    - Boatman, Edward (Box 7)
    - Bolcom, William (Box 7)
    - Burgie, Irving (Box 7)
    - Coleridge, Taylor (Box 7)
    - De Priest, James (Box 7)
    - Ellington, Duke (Box 7)
    - Grant, Micki (Box 7)
    - Joplin, Scott (Box 7)
    - Kay, Ullysses (Box 7)
    - King, Betty J. (Box 7)
    - Lee, Everett (Box 7)
    - Moore, Dorothy (Box 7)
    - Ramos, Ethel (Box 7)
    - Saint-George, Chevalier (Box 7)
    - Schuyler, Philippa (Box 7)
    - Still, William Grant (Box 7)
    - Swanson, Howard (Box 7)
    - White, Clarence (Box 7)
  - Chorus and Orchestras (Box 8)
    - Afro-Americans of the Philadelphia Orchestra 1976 (Box 8)
    - Decormel Folk Singers (Box 8)
    - Convent Avenue Baptist Church Choir (Box 8)
    - Davis Family Choir (Box 8)
    - Fisk Jubilee Singers (Box 8)
    - Harlem Philharmonic (Box 8)
    - Metropolitan Chorus (Box 8)
    - Martin Luther King Male Glee Club of NYC (Box 8)
    - Oberlin Black Ensemble (Box 8)
    - Symphony of the New World (Box 8)
  - Actors, Dancers, Educators, Entertainers, Historic Figures, Poets, Writers
    - Aldrige, Ira (Box 8)
    - Anderson, Thomas (Box 8)
    - Angelou, Maya (Box 8)
    - Arvey, Verna (Box 8)
    - Baldwin, James (Box 8)
    - Bethune, Mary McLeod (Box 8)
    - Brooks. Gwendolyn (Box 8)
    - Bullins, Ed (Box 8)
    - Burke, Georgia (Box 8)
    - Burton, Levar (Box 8)
    - Carroll, Diahann (Box 8)
    - Castor, Jimmy (Box 8)
    - Cosby, Bill (Box 8)
    - Davis, Ossie (Box 8)
    - Daughtry, Willia (Box 8)
    - Dillard, James (Box 8)
    - Dubois, W.E.B. (Box 8)
    - Dunbar, Paul Laurence (Box 8)
    - Giovanni, Nikki (Box 8)
    - Hale, Birdie (Box 8)
    - Haley, Alex (Box 8)
    - Hughes, Langston (Box 8)
    - Hansberry, Lorraine (Box 8)
    - Jones, James Earl (Box 8)
    - King, Martin Luther (Box 8)
    - Lance, Leon (Box 8)
    - Marshall, Thurgood (Box 8)
    - McDaniel, Hattie (Box 8)
    - McNair, Barbara (Box 8)
    - McNeil, Claudia (Box 8)
    - Peters, Brock (Box 8)
    - Poitier, Sidney (Box 8)
    - Premice, Josephine (Box 8)
    - Redding, J. Saunders (Box 8)
    - Robinson, Bill "Bojangles" (Box 8)
    - Roundtree, Richard (Box 8)
    - Schroeder, Gerald H. (Box 8)
    - Silvera, Frank (Box 8)
    - Simms, Hilda (Box 8)
    - Tubman, Harriet (Box 8)
    - Tyson, Cicely (Box 8)
    - Uggams, Leslie (Box 8)
    - Washington, Chet (Box 8)
    - Ward, Douglas Turner (Box 8)
    - Williams, Billy Dee (Box 8)
    - Wilson, Flip (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous Clippings (Box 8)
  - Oversized Clippings (located in Box 14) (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photograph series (3.0 linear feet and one outsized box) contains photographs of Jessye and her friends and family, many pictures of various Eva Jessye Choirs, scene shots and individual publicity shots for various Porgy and Bess casts, and publicity shots of performing artists, black cultural leaders and political leaders. This collection is an excellent visual survey of Afro-American cultural history. This series is derived from a number of binders and is organized by photo content and binder. The binder provenance is recorded on the folder when known. Many of these photographs are well labeled. Each folder is grouped into one of eight subseries: Eva Jessye; The Eva Jessye Choir; Choirs, Dance and Theatrical Groups; Scene Shots; Clippings; Programs; Unclassifiable; Porgy and Bess; and Black History. The Black History subseries collects many photographs, generally 8x10, of African American social activists and people in the arts. Some of those included are Alvin Ailey, Eddie Anderson, Marian Anderson, James Baldwin, Howlin' Wolf, Ray Charles, Gloria Davy, Katherine Dunham, Lionel Hampton, The Nicolas Brothers, Leontyne Price, Billy Taylor, and Stevie Wonder.
  - Photo Drawer List (Box 9)
  - Eva Jessye
    - Jessye with Family -- Binder A (Box 9)
    - Jessye -- Binder D (Box 9)
    - Framed Photos (Box 9)
    - Large Brown Photo Album (Box 9)
    - Un-labeled Maroon Binders (Box 9)
    - Loose Photographs
      - Small Floral Photo Album (Box 9)
      - Dedication at University of Michigan 1974 (Box 9)
      - Etta Moten Photos (Box 9)
      - Posters, Flyers, News Clippings (Box 9)
      - Conducting Paradise Lost 1979 (Box 9)
      - Ancestors, Buckners in St. Louis (Box 9)
      - Family (Box 9)
      - In Character with Standifer (Box 9)
      - At Stern and Dedication 1974 (Box 9)
      - University of Michigan Small Choir (Box 9)
      - Friends at the Piano, Negatives (Box 9)
      - With Sylvia Lee and Everett Lee, Negatives (Box 9)
      - Loose (Box 9)
  - Eva Jessye Choir
    - Binder D (Box 9)
    - Display Materials (Box 9)
  - Choirs
    - Binder A (Box 9)
    - Binder B (Box 9)
    - Binder C (Box 9)
  - Dance and Theatre Groups
    - Alvin Alley -- Binder A (Box 9)
    - H. Tann Theatrical Ensemble -- Binder B (Box 9)
  - Scene Shots
    - Binder A (Box 9)
    - Binder B (Box 9)
    - Binder C (Box 9)
    - Binder D (Box 9)
  - Clippings, Programs, Unclassifiable, Photocopies
    - Production Clippings and Programs -- Binder A (Box 9)
    - Unclassifiable -- Binder A (Box 9)
    - Production Clippings and Unclassifiable -- Binder B (Box 9)
    - Production Clippings and Programs -- Binder C (Box 9)
    - Unclassifiable -- Binder C (Box 9)
    - Production Clippings and Programs -- Binder D (Box 9)
    - Known Photographs (Box 9)
    - Partially Known Photographs (Box 9)
    - Unknown Photographs (Box 9)
    - Loose Photographs, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Photocopies (Box 9)
  - Porgy and Bess
    - Publicity Shots, Individuals --RSB2 (Box 10)
    - Publicity Shots, Individuals --Maroon 2" Binder (Box 10)
    - Publicity Shots and Scene Shots, Black 1" Binder (Box 10)
    - Publicity Shots and Scene Shots, Black 1.5" Binder (Box 10)
    - Publicity Shots and Scene Shots, in Pittsburg, RSB2 1942 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots, RSB2 1958 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots in Egypt, RSB2 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots in Boston, RSB2 1942 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots, Maroon 2" Binder 1976 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots, Maroon 2" Binder 1935 (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots, Maroon 2" Binder, New Zealand (Box 10)
    - Scene Shots, Orpheus, Maroon Binder #3 (Box 10)
    - Proofs and Miscellaneous, RSB2 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, Maroon Binder #1 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous, Maroon Binder #2 (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Shots, Blue 2" Binder (Box 10)
    - Miscellaneous Loose Photos (Box 10)
    - Snaps, Cast and Scene, Negatives, Clippings, Red 3" Binder, 3 folders (Box 10)
  - Photo Lists (Box 11)
  - Black History Photos
    - Publicity Shots
      - Individuals, 9 folders (Box 11)
      - Individuals, Binder A, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Individuals, Maroon 2" Binder (Box 11)
      - Individuals, Framed (Box 11)
      - Individuals, Opera Stars (Box 11)
      - Group Shots, 2 folders (Box 11)
      - Group Shots, Binder B (Box 11)
      - Group Shots, Binder C, The Talented Turners (Box 11)
      - Group Shots, Binder D (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous Individual and Group Shots (Box 11)
    - Prints of Black Americans (Box 11)
    - Unidentified Family Shots, Maroon 2" Binder (Box 11)
  - Oversized Black History Photos (located in Box 14) (Box 11)
  - Miscellaneous Scene Shots, 2 folders (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Production Clippings and Programs (Box 12)
  - Miscellaneous Publicity Shots (Box 12)
- Awards, Certificates, and Proclamations
  The Awards and Certificates series (1 outsized box) collects documents honoring Jessye including the award for Kansas Ambassador of the Arts, honorary proclamations from California, Kansas, Oklahoma, Pennsylvania, Atlanta, Dallas, Los Angeles, Memphis, New York City, Philadelphia, St. Louis, Taft, Oklahoma, and Washington DC. Among other tributes, Jessye also received honors from Howard University and Pittsburg State University in Kansas, and honorary doctorates from the University of Michigan School of Music, Eastern Michigan University and Glassboro State College.
  - Awards and Certificates, Originals, 7 folders; 3 oversize items (Box 13)
  - Awards and Certificates, Copies (Box 13)
  - Certification of Appreciation, International Freedom Festival (Box 14)
  - County of Los Angeles honor (Box 14)
- Eva Jessye Program Series (outsized)
  - Concert Posters Involving Jessye or concerts organized by the Eva Jessye Collection (Box 14)
- Collected Program Series (outsized)
  - Concert Posters, University of Michigan and Ann Arbor (Box 14)
- Black History Clippings (outsized)
  - Miscellaneous Black History Material (Box 14)
- Photographs (outsized)
  - Black History Photos (outsized)
    - Miscellaneous Publicity shots, individual and group (Box 14)
Related Material
For more information on Eva Jessye see the Leonard H. Axe Library at Pittsburg State University in Kansas, which holds a 5 linear foot collection of her papers and records: http://library.pittstate.edu/spcoll/ndxjessye.html
The Robert W. Woodruff Library of the Atlanta University Center (http://www.auctr.edu/rwwl/Home/tabid/437/Default.aspx) also has a small Eva Jessye collection: http://www.auctr.edu/rwwl/FindingAids%5CEva%20Jessye%20Collection.pdf